<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>TheDevtop</title>
    <link>https://thedevtop.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on TheDevtop</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 19:25:35 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://thedevtop.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>UVM: A secret love letter</title>
      <link>https://thedevtop.github.io/uvm-a-secret-love-letter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Oct 2023 19:25:35 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://thedevtop.github.io/uvm-a-secret-love-letter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I had some DIMM corruption, which led me to decommission one of my machines.
The hole situation got me thinking about the fragility of software and how not even the most elegant abstraction can save you from the grim reality of hardware failure.
It also happens to be a good reason to talk about one of my favorite pieces of software: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usenix.org/legacy/event/usenix99/full_papers/cranor/cranor.pdf&#34;&gt;The UVM Virtual Memory System&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;let-there-be-light&#34;&gt;Let there be light&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UVM is the virtual memory subsystem used in the kernels of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.openbsd.org/&#34;&gt;OpenBSD&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.netbsd.org/&#34;&gt;NetBSD&lt;/a&gt;.
It was written to replace the old (4.4BSD) virtual memory subsystem, which was a modified version of the one found in Carnegie Mellon&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mach_(kernel)&#34;&gt;Mach&lt;/a&gt; microkernel.
The reason for replacement was straightforward: Poor performance, complex data structures, and poor documentation.
Which is quite funny because today (2023) the best documentation I could find about the Mach VM comes from &lt;a href=&#34;https://developer.apple.com/documentation/kernel/mach/vm&#34;&gt;Apple&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://web.mit.edu/darwin/src/modules/xnu/osfmk/man/&#34;&gt;MIT&lt;/a&gt;, not from Carnegie Mellon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason for UVM is the classic triad: Simplicity, performance, and maintainability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;masters-of-architecture&#34;&gt;Masters of architecture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a great VM implementation is one thing, but having a great paper to companion it is something else entirely.
With UVM, Cranor and Parulkar give us both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://thedevtop.github.io/uvm_arch.png&#34; alt=&#34;uvm_arch&#34;&gt;
The architecture is easy to understand.
The &lt;em&gt;vmspace&lt;/em&gt; structure contains pointers to a process’s &lt;em&gt;pmap&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;memory map&lt;/em&gt; structures, it also contains some statistics.
The &lt;em&gt;pmap&lt;/em&gt; is the machine-dependent structure, while the &lt;em&gt;memory map&lt;/em&gt; is the machine-independent structure that holds the memory objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some observations: The various segments (text/data/stack) are seperate objects, which is beneficial for security.
The objects can be of many types, and backed by many &lt;em&gt;pagers&lt;/em&gt;.
The important thing here, is that these types and pagers can be implemented by &lt;strong&gt;other&lt;/strong&gt; kernel subsystems (which I think is so cool).
Finally, UVM allows for anonymous mapping, which is usefull if you have two processes that map the same object (like the text segment of &lt;code&gt;/bin/sh&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-sound-of-memory&#34;&gt;The sound of memory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Managing (virtual) memory is not easy, and implementing a good VM is definitely not easy. But UVM manages to do it while retaining flexibility and an astonishingly simple architecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simplicity while managing &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kernel_(operating_system)&#34;&gt;Heaven and Earth&lt;/a&gt;, is why UVM remains my favorite piece of software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sources&#34;&gt;Sources&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/NetBSD/src/tree/trunk/sys/uvm&#34;&gt;NetBSD Kernel/UVM (Source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/openbsd/src/tree/master/sys/uvm&#34;&gt;OpenBSD Kernel/UVM (Source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/openmach/openmach/tree/master/kernel/vm&#34;&gt;OpenMach VM (Source)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usenix.org/legacy/events/usenix2000/freenix/full_papers/silvers/silvers.pdf&#34;&gt;Unified Buffer Cache (Paper)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    
  </channel>
</rss>
